<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Prateek Dayal]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.prateekdayal.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.prateekdayal.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-09T08:55:50+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.prateekdayal.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Prateek Dayal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling Inspired]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.prateekdayal.net/feeling-inspired"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T18:10:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.prateekdayal.net/feeling-inspired</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my younger days, I found inspiration only in a very limited number of things &ndash; seeing great technology in action, reading a great book and ofcourse  in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Founders-Work-Stories-Startups-Early/dp/1590597141">Founders at Work</a>. I had a hard time appreciating great work in industries or domains that I was not familiar with. What&rsquo;s more, I really felt no need to look deeper elsewhere. That changed in the last few years as I traveled more and talked to more people from different walks of life. Conversations with people outside technology or startup world helped me see new perspectives on things I had always interacted with before, but never paid much attention to. Things like well cooked meals, an attention to the lights in a restaurant or a bar or just better run airlines and more well designed real life systems. It was amazing to me how much difference attention to details in these things mattered and changed your experience as a consumer. Just like it&rsquo;s always amazing to watch great programmers code and talk about code, I was amazed watching a great hairdresser in action or an office manager at work.</p>

<p>I still look up to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Dorsey">Jack Dorsey</a> or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elon_Musk">Elon Musk</a> for inspiration but now I also find it around me in people and things that I did not observe closely before. They inspire me to do great work and serve my customers better as much as the role models I have in the startup world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Thoughts - New Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.prateekdayal.net/new-blog"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T16:08:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.prateekdayal.net/new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last few years, I almost neglected my personal blog. I got busy with SupportBee and travel but the bigger reason was that I wasn&rsquo;t sure of what to write about on my blog. A lot of my writing involved SupportBee and technology and went on the SupportBee Blog and Devblog. Also short thoughts went on to Twitter.</p>

<p>The last time I wrote about a new experience was back in September 2010 when I wrote about the <a href="http://www.prateekdayal.net/2010/09/19/why-we-nee-more-lifestyle-businesses/">cafe culture in Vietnam</a>. Since then I have traveled a lot more, met a lot more people and had a chance to think about life and work. Lately, I feel the urge to write again and write about more things. Not just startups but many other experiences and perspectives. Since this is a very different theme from my old blog, I have decided to archive my old blog and start afresh. I welcome you to my new blog. I hope to post atleast once a month on things that interest me personally. Thank you for reading :)</p>

<p>I am using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> for this blog, which was very easy to install and setup on Github. Thank you Octopress!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
